Leah: How a person feels about
themselves and many different pressures
growing up can affect a child’s or
young person’s self-esteem, such as
social media, bullying, exams, family
problems, gender issues and abuse.
Rhiannon: Most children will have dips
in self-esteem as they go through life.
Starting a new school, moving house,
changes in the family and many
other factors can affect a child’s
confidence, but with support from
parents and other adults in their lives
they usually get them through this.
Leah: Children and young people with
high self-esteem often have a positive
image of themselves and are confident,
make friends easily, and will try
new things and adapt to change.
They often are happy on their own or in
a group and will try to solve problems
for themselves and if they make mistakes
will learn from them, ultimately
becoming proud of their achievements.
Children and young people with low
self-esteem often have a negative image
of themselves, they might feel bad, ugly,
unlikeable or stupid, lack in confidence
and are constantly comparing themselves
to their peers in a negative way.
They may feel lonely and isolated finding
it hard to make and keep friendships
or feeling victimised by others.
They tend to avoid new things, finding
change hard and can't deal well with
their own failure, putting themselves
down and not proud of achievement, always
thinking they could have done better.